<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Matthew Thomas Miller ماتیو توماس میلر</title>
    <description>Assistant Professor of Persian Literature and Digital Humanities at Roshan Institute for Persian Studies, University of Maryland, College Park</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<<<<<<< HEAD
    <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 12:01:09 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 12:01:09 -0400</lastBuildDate>
=======
    <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 13:58:21 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 13:58:21 -0400</lastBuildDate>
>>>>>>> 1d3d2e6898f77bc06ded3dc524d00ebdd6658466
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Course: Sex, Love, and Desire in Persian Poetry</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sex, Love, and Desire in Persian Poetry&lt;/em&gt; will provide students with a survey of the permutations of desire—sexual to sacred, heteroerotic to homoerotic—in Persian literature from its earliest works (e.g., &lt;em&gt;Shah-Nameh&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Vis and Ramin&lt;/em&gt;) to modern “new poetry” (&lt;em&gt;she’r-e now&lt;/em&gt;) (e.g., Farrokhzad, Shams).  The course will be divided up into four units: (1) romantic epic; (2) Sufi “sacred” love literature; (3) bawdy verse and erotic advice literature; (4) modern “new” love poetry. The chronological and generic breadth of the course will enable us to study the ways in which authors of various times and places adapt and transform amorous themes for their own time and literary aims. We will also study the changing “politics of desire” (e.g., the highly political ways in which modern readers and literary critics have responded to the manifest homoerotic and other non-heteronormative forms of desire in premodern Persian literature). In addition to the readings/topics on the syllabus, students will have the opportunity to engage in their own independent research on a topic of their own choice related to Persian literature (in consultation with the instructor), which they will report on in the form of a class presentation and final project. The course neither presupposes nor requires any knowledge of the Persian language or prior coursework in Persian literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please contact me if you are interested in reviewing the full syllabus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/Course-Sex-Love-and-Desire-in-Persian-Poetry/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/Course-Sex-Love-and-Desire-in-Persian-Poetry/</guid>
        
        <category>Persian</category>
        
        <category>Literature,</category>
        
        <category>Course,</category>
        
        <category>Sex,</category>
        
        <category>Gender,</category>
        
        <category>Sexuality,</category>
        
        <category>Poetry,</category>
        
        <category>Shah-Nameh,</category>
        
        <category>Vis</category>
        
        <category>and</category>
        
        <category>Ramin,</category>
        
        <category>Rumi,</category>
        
        <category>'Eraqi,</category>
        
        <category>Sana'i,</category>
        
        <category>Qabus-Nameh,</category>
        
        <category>Forugh</category>
        
        <category>Farrokhzad,</category>
        
        <category>Simin</category>
        
        <category>Behbahani,</category>
        
        <category>Fatemeh</category>
        
        <category>Shams</category>
        
        
        <category>Course</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Course: Sex, Gender, and Sexuality in the Islamic World</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CourseFlyerSexGenderSexualityIslamicWorld.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sex, Gender, and Sexuality in the Islamic World, taught by Matthew Thomas Miller&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;   &lt;br /&gt;
[Note: First taught in Spring 2017, revised Fall 2018]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sex, Gender, and Sexuality in the Islamic World&lt;/em&gt; is an advanced introduction to the study of the changing norms of sex, gender, and sexuality in the Islamicate world, past and present. Through engagement with primary source readings, recent scholarly studies, and theoretical literature from Gender and Sexuality Studies and Queer Theory, we will cover such topics as: Islamic sexual ethics; homo- and heteroerotic poetry and art of both the spiritual and profane varieties; transvestism, androgyny, and gender nonconformity in the medieval Islamic world; premodern Islamic medical and courtly advice literature on sex; and the construction of “sexuality” (homo- and heterosexuality) in the modern Middle East. The course does not require  any prior knowledge of Gender and Sexuality Studies or Islamicate cultures and languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please contact me if you are interested in reviewing the full syllabus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/Course-Sex-Gender-and-Sexuality-in-the-Islamic-World/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/Course-Sex-Gender-and-Sexuality-in-the-Islamic-World/</guid>
        
        <category>Islamic</category>
        
        <category>Studies,</category>
        
        <category>Course,</category>
        
        <category>Sex,</category>
        
        <category>Gender,</category>
        
        <category>Sexuality</category>
        
        
        <category>Course</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Course: The Islamicate World 2.0: Studying Islamic Cultures through Computational Textual Analysis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CourseFlyerIslamicateWorld2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Islamicate World 2.0: Studying Islamic Cultures through Computational Textual Analysis, taught by Matthew Thomas Miller &amp;amp; Maxim Romanov&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to Global Digital Humanities&lt;/em&gt; seeks to provide a more ‘global’ window on the field of Digital Humanities (DH) and its associated technologies. Building on other critical approaches to DH (e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;http://dhpoco.org/&quot;&gt;Postcolonial Digital Humanities&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://transformdh.org/&quot;&gt;#TransformDH&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.globaloutlookdh.org/&quot;&gt;Global Outlook::Digital Humanities (GO::DH)&lt;/a&gt;), it aims to both constructively problematize DH as a field from multiple ‘peripheral’ perspectives and introduce students to some of the technologies they can utilize to make DH more ‘global.’ The ‘global’ in ‘Global DH’ is meant in two senses: we will foreground contributions to and critiques of DH from both the widest possible geographic range and other (digital) communities that are peripheral in the DH field due their linguistic, racial, sexual, or technological particularities. There are no requirements for this course and it does not presuppose that students have any particular background in the DH field. Students interested in theoretical debates within DH, practical applications of DH methods to literary studies, or the purely technical dimensions of DH work (coding, statistics, etc.) are all welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the course is available &lt;a href=&quot;http://islamicate-dh.github.io/IW2Course_2016/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/Course-The-Islamicate-World-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/Course-The-Islamicate-World-2/</guid>
        
        <category>Digital</category>
        
        <category>Humanities,</category>
        
        <category>Course</category>
        
        
        <category>Course</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Course: Introduction to Global Digital Humanities</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/GlobalDHFlyer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Introduction to Persian Literature in Translation, taught by Matthew Thomas Miller&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to Global Digital Humanities&lt;/em&gt; seeks to provide a more ‘global’ window on the field of Digital Humanities (DH) and its associated technologies. Building on other critical approaches to DH (e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;http://dhpoco.org/&quot;&gt;Postcolonial Digital Humanities&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://transformdh.org/&quot;&gt;#TransformDH&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.globaloutlookdh.org/&quot;&gt;Global Outlook::Digital Humanities (GO::DH)&lt;/a&gt;), it aims to both constructively problematize DH as a field from multiple ‘peripheral’ perspectives and introduce students to some of the technologies they can utilize to make DH more ‘global.’ The ‘global’ in ‘Global DH’ is meant in two senses: we will foreground contributions to and critiques of DH from both the widest possible geographic range and other (digital) communities that are peripheral in the DH field due their linguistic, racial, sexual, or technological particularities. There are no requirements for this course and it does not presuppose that students have any particular background in the DH field. Students interested in theoretical debates within DH, practical applications of DH methods to literary studies, or the purely technical dimensions of DH work (coding, statistics, etc.) are all welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please contact me if you are interested in reviewing the full syllabus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/Course-Introduction-to-Global-Digital-Humanities/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/Course-Introduction-to-Global-Digital-Humanities/</guid>
        
        <category>Digital</category>
        
        <category>Humanities,</category>
        
        <category>Course</category>
        
        
        <category>Course</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>List of Persian-related Sessions at the 2016 Modern Language Association Convention</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mla2016.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Persian-related Sessions at the 2016 Modern Language Association Convention&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a list of the #MLA2016 sessions that have papers on Persian-related topics. (Please do let me know if I have missed any and I will revise and update!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.mla.org/conv_listings_detail?prog_id=97&amp;amp;year=2016&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;97. Translations between Center and Periphery: From Iran to the West&lt;/strong&gt;
Thursday, 7 January, 3:30–4:45 p.m., 402, JW Marriott&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Program arranged by the forum LLC West Asian&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presiding: Amy Motlagh, American Univ. in Cairo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speakers:Esmaeil Haddadian-Moghaddam, Univ. of Leuven; Franklin Lewis, Univ. of Chicago; Laetitia Nanquette, Univ. of New South Wales; Nasrin Rahimieh, Univ. of California, Irvine; Kamran Rastegar, Tufts Univ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Session Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Translations from Persian into European languages are an important but often overlooked part of the history of the idea of world literature. By studying translation flows between Iran and Western countries, panelists seek to question the absence of Persian in most discussions of world literature and to situate translation experiences in a global context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.mla.org/conv_listings_detail?prog_id=606&amp;amp;year=2016&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;606. “Imagined” Performance Contexts in Medieval Persian Literature&lt;/strong&gt;
Saturday, 9 January, 1:45–3:00 p.m., 404, JW Marriott&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A special session&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presiding: Austin O’Malley, Univ. of Chicago&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“In My Own Words: Songs and Letters in the Early Persian Romance,” Cameron Cross, Univ. of Michigan, Ann Arbor&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Embodying the Beloved in Textual-Performance Contexts: A Queer Reading of Medieval Biographical and Hagiographical Accounts of Poetic Performance,” Matthew Thomas Miller, Washington Univ. in St. Louis&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Preaching through Text: ʿAṭṭâr and the Homiletics of Transformation,” Austin O’Malley&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Textually Divided: Performance Context and the Model Reader in ‘The Suffering Lover,’” Amin Azad Sadr, Salt Lake City, UT&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.mla.org/conv_listings_detail?prog_id=658&amp;amp;year=2016&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;658. Contemporary Literature and the Forever Wars&lt;/strong&gt;
Saturday, 9 January, 5:15–6:30 p.m., 18A, ACC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A special session&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presiding: Aaron DeRosa, California State Polytechnic Univ., Pomona&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speakers: Patrick Deer, New York Univ.; A. B. Huber, New York Univ.; Ikram Masmoudi, Univ. of Delaware, Newark; Peter Molin, Rutgers Univ., New Brunswick; Stacey L. Peebles, Centre Coll.; Roy Scranton, Princeton Univ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For position papers, visit https://contemporarywar.commons.mla.org/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Session Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Panelists initiate a dialogue about the emergent body of Iraq and Afghanistan War writing at a moment in which the wars have reasserted themselves representationally after years of silence. Our diverse set of scholars seeks to engage contemporary war writing before it becomes crystallized into a canon or relegated to what Edna Longley has called the “ghetto of war literature.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.mla.org/conv_listings_detail?prog_id=742&amp;amp;year=2016&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;742. Novel Thinking: Contemporary Literature without Form&lt;/strong&gt;
Sunday, 10 January, 10:15–11:30 a.m., 208, JW Marriott&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A special session&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presiding: Christopher Holmes, Ithaca Coll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The Problem of Expression: Lessons from (Iranian) Cinema,” Timothy Bewes, Brown Univ.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“J. M. Coetzee on the Novel’s Alterity Effect,” Dorothy J. Hale, Univ. of California, Berkeley&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“At the Limit: Novel Thinking against Form,” Christopher Holmes&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For abstracts, visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://persian.commons.mla.org/&quot;&gt;https://persian.commons.mla.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/List-of-Persian-related-Sessions-at-the-2016-MLA/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/List-of-Persian-related-Sessions-at-the-2016-MLA/</guid>
        
        <category>MLA,</category>
        
        <category>Modern</category>
        
        <category>Language</category>
        
        <category>Association</category>
        
        <category>Convention,</category>
        
        <category>Persian</category>
        
        <category>Literature</category>
        
        
        <category>Conference</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Course: Introduction to Persian Literature in Translations</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CourseFlyerIntroPersianLit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Introduction to Persian Literature in Translation, taught by Matthew Thomas Miller&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;
[Note: First taught in Spring 2015, revised Fall 2017]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction to Persian Literature in Translation&lt;/em&gt; aims to provide the student with a general introduction to the (New) Persian literary tradition, beginning with the &lt;em&gt;Book of Kings (Shah-Nameh)&lt;/em&gt; (composed in the late 10th/early 11th century) and concluding with the “New Poetry” (&lt;em&gt;she’r-e now&lt;/em&gt;), modern novels, and other emerging textual forms (e.g., slam poetry) of twentieth and twenty-first century Iran. It requires no knowledge of the Persian language or prior course work in Persian literature. Through close readings of works by many of the most important authors in Persian literature and a limited number of secondary studies, the student will come to be acquainted with the basic contours of the Persian literary tradition, including its principal generic forms and important historical transformations. Students will also have the opportunity to engage in their own independent research on several topics of their own choice related to Persian literature (in consultation with the instructor), which they will report on in the form of a class presentation and final project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please contact me if you are interested in reviewing the full syllabus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2015/Course-Introduction-to-Persian-Literature-in-Translation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2015/Course-Introduction-to-Persian-Literature-in-Translation/</guid>
        
        <category>Course,</category>
        
        <category>Persian</category>
        
        <category>Literature,</category>
        
        <category>Shah-Nameh,</category>
        
        <category>New</category>
        
        <category>Poetry,</category>
        
        <category>Rumi,</category>
        
        <category>'Attar,</category>
        
        <category>'Eraqi,</category>
        
        <category>Khaqani,</category>
        
        <category>Sohrab</category>
        
        <category>Sepehri,</category>
        
        <category>Forugh</category>
        
        <category>Farrokhzad,</category>
        
        <category>Parvin</category>
        
        <category>E’tesami,</category>
        
        <category>Nima</category>
        
        <category>Yushij,</category>
        
        <category>Ahmad</category>
        
        <category>Shamlu,</category>
        
        <category>Siavash</category>
        
        <category>Kasra’i,</category>
        
        <category>and</category>
        
        <category>Simin</category>
        
        <category>Behbahani,</category>
        
        <category>Sadeq</category>
        
        <category>Hedayat,</category>
        
        <category>M.A.</category>
        
        <category>Jamalzadeh,</category>
        
        <category>Bozorg</category>
        
        <category>Alavi</category>
        
        
        <category>Course</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Course: Lyrics of Mystical Love, East and West</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lyrics of Mystical Love: East and West&lt;/em&gt; is a journey through the mystical love poetry of some of the world’s most important mystical poets: Rumi, Ibn ‘Arabi, St. John of the Cross, St. Teresa of Ávila, amongst many others. Like any journey, this journey will require certain preparations and provisions. We will need to prepare ourselves for this adventure by studying the religious, social, and political contexts in which these mystical poets wrote (e.g. Ernst) and also discuss some of the (theoretical) pitfalls that others have identified along the route (e.g., King). Ultimately, however, this journey is a poetic journey. In other words, the class and its projects will primarily revolve around visits to the poetic worlds of different poets. We will examine the work of each poet through a variety of different lens of literary analysis (e.g., Culler) and also read a number of works that exemplify the literary approach to analysis of mystical poetry (e.g., Keshavarz, Sells).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please contact me if you are interested in reviewing the full syllabus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2014/Course-Lyrics-of-Mystical-Love-East-and-West/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2014/Course-Lyrics-of-Mystical-Love-East-and-West/</guid>
        
        <category>Mysticism,</category>
        
        <category>Poetry,</category>
        
        <category>Rumi,</category>
        
        <category>'Attar,</category>
        
        <category>Meister</category>
        
        <category>Eckhart,</category>
        
        <category>Ibn</category>
        
        <category>'Arabi,</category>
        
        <category>Marguerite</category>
        
        <category>Porete,</category>
        
        <category>Teresa</category>
        
        <category>of</category>
        
        <category>Ávila,</category>
        
        <category>John</category>
        
        <category>of</category>
        
        <category>the</category>
        
        <category>Cross,</category>
        
        <category>Course</category>
        
        
        <category>Course</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>'The Kite Runner' Critiqued: New Orientalism Goes to the Big Screen</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/kiterunner.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Kite Runner movie, based on Khaled Hosseini's bestselling book&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While &lt;em&gt;The Kite Runner&lt;/em&gt; movie is now captivating audiences throughout the country-much as the book did four years ago-with its enthralling tale of “family, forgiveness, and friendship” and the promise that indeed “there is a way to be good again,” very little has been written critiquing this work and its prominent role in the New Orientalist narrative of the Islamic Middle East. Read the rest &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.commondreams.org/views/2008/01/05/kite-runner-critiqued-new-orientalism-goes-big-screen&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2008 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2008/The-Kite-Runner-Critiqued/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2008/The-Kite-Runner-Critiqued/</guid>
        
        <category>Kite</category>
        
        <category>Runner,</category>
        
        <category>New</category>
        
        <category>Orientalism,</category>
        
        <category>Khaled</category>
        
        <category>Hosseini,</category>
        
        <category>Afghanistan,</category>
        
        <category>Public</category>
        
        <category>Scholarship,</category>
        
        <category>Orientalism</category>
        
        
        <category>public</category>
        
        <category>scholarship</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
